Hey, hey, what's up, my friend? So, I
have read hundreds of books on trading.
You know, books on technical analysis,
chart patterns, Amazon best sellers,
books that are so thick that they can
even stop a shooting bullet. And some
books that are so bad that they should
give me a refund and a formal apology
for wasting my time. And after all this
reading, I found out that, you know, 95%
of these books, they are useless. They
are not wrong per se, but useless at
actually putting money in your pocket.
At the same time,
among the hundreds of books that I've
read, there are actually a few that
transformed my trading. It took me from
a losing trader to a consistently
profitable one.
As you can see, this is my trading
results
over here, right? You can see that I've
made over 343% over the last 7 years and
compared to the S&P 500, which made
about
118%
over here.
I've traded through COVID,
Russia-Ukraine war, low inflation
period, high inflation period, Trump's
liberation day, and still I've come out
ahead and beaten the markets
consistently. Now, how did I do it? It's
not because I'm smart, a genius, or
whatsoever, but rather, if you ask me,
it's because of these books that I'm
about to share with you.
Sounds good? Then let's get to it. The
first book is Market Wizards by Jack
Schwager.
Now, when you're starting out as a
trader, you don't know what works and
what doesn't work. Everyone on the
internet claims
is the best. You know, every guru has a
secret method. And every thumbnail has
that perfect-looking chart that doesn't
work in the live markets. So, who do you
trust? That's why Market Wizards is such
a useful book because, instead of
learning from random dudes on YouTube or
social media, you're learning from
experienced traders with verified track
records.
And people who have actually made
millions and some even billions from the
markets. This book interviews many of
these traders and here's what I've
learned.
Number one, you must have an edge in the
markets. All right, an edge is something
that you do repeatedly over time that
yields a positive outcome. Because
without it, even the best risk
management or discipline won't make you
a profitable trader. That's how
important it is. To give you an example,
right? Imagine you go down to the
casino.
You bring along the best psychologist to
help you with your uh discipline.
You practice sound risk management.
Now, let me ask you. Are you going to
beat the casino in the long run? Are you
going to extract a profit from the
casino?
The answer is no. Why is that? It's
because you don't have an edge over the
house. And that's what I mean. Number
two, there are many ways to find an edge
in the markets. In Market Wizards,
you'll realize that there are traders
using different strategies to profit
from the markets, you know, things like
trend following, some does macro
trading, some does arbitrage, some some
uses options. So, there are many ways to
profit from the market and ultimately,
you need to find a approach, an approach
that actually suits your personality.
So, this reminds me of
one trader that I've come across. I
believe his name is Marty Schwartz. He
was a analyst on Wall Street for 9
years.
He used fundamentals
to trade the markets, to try to profit
from the markets, and he failed. And the
moment he swapped for from fundamentals
to technicals, that's where he became a
consistently profitable trader. Now,
that is not to say that fundamentals
doesn't work, right? Because you have
people like Warren Buffett, you know,
making a
uh killing, right? Using fundamentals.
But, you need to find an approach that
suits your personality.
And one thing that I also noticed in
Market Wizards was that, you know, many
of these traders were trading in a
similar manner. They were actually
riding trends till it ends. And this
sounded appealing to me. Sounds like
something that, you know, would suit my
personality. So, I figured that this is
a strategy that I wanted to learn more
and this brought me to my next book.
Here's something you're probably unaware
of.
In 2008, the S&P 500 plunged 37% you
know, sending shockwaves across the
global markets.
However, when everyone was you know,
selling their kidneys to cover margin
calls, a small group of traders, they
were quietly making a fortune.
Mulvaney Capital gained 100% while most
fund managers were updating their
resumes. Dunn Capital made over 50%
during this period and Graham Capital
finished the year up about 36%. It's
like owning a toilet paper company
during COVID, you know, when everybody
is panicking, you're printing cash.
So, how did these hedge funds do it?
They actually adopt a trend following
strategy and thus the second book is
Trend Following by Michael Covel.
This book goes deep into trend
following. It explains what trend
following is about, why it works and the
principles behind it. And even explain
you know, how it's actually being used
by billion-dollar hedge funds to profit
in bull and bear markets, especially
during a crisis or recession period.
The idea behind trend following is
simple. You ride the trend
till it ends. And to make trend
following work, here are four principles
that you must adopt.
Number one, you want to trade many
different types of markets to increase
your odds of capturing a trend. So, what
I mean by this is that you don't want to
just only trade
10, 20 different currency pairs because
they are correlated to a certain degree
like you know, euro dollar, Aussie
dollar, New Zealand dollar, you know,
those are not enough. You need to be
expanding your universe. You need need
to be trading different currency pairs,
different indices like you know, S&P
500, the Nikkei, the ASX. You need to be
trading the metals like gold, silver,
platinum, palladium. You'll be trading
oil. You'll be trading agriculture
markets like soybean, wheat, corn, etc.
So, this
by trading all these different types of
markets out there, the different futures
market, you increase your odds of
capturing a trend.
Number two, you need to also risk a
fraction of your capitals on each trade
so you can live to fight another day.
The reason is simple, it's because trend
following
by nature, this strategy has a low
winning rate, about 40% winning rate.
So, you'll face losses pretty often, in
fact, most of the time. So, the only way
to survive these losses, to live to
fight another day, is to have sound risk
management. Not losing more than 1% of
your account on each trade. I think this
hedge funds, some of them they just risk
like, you know, a fraction of 1%, maybe
0.5 or 0.25% on each trade.
And third thing, you need to use a
trailing stop loss to ride the trend.
So, a trailing stop loss is a technique
that allows you to lock in your gains as
the market progressively moved in your
favor.
So, here's how it works. So, let's say
for example, you buy,
you know, let's say something like the
S&P 500.
Okay, let's say let's say a a stock, all
right, to to simplify it. The stock goes
up, comes down, goes up, comes down,
goes up, and then breaks out. Let's say
as a trend follower, you buy at $100
when the thing breaks up. Then the
trend develop,
and let's say over here the highest is
$200.
Now, let's say you have a 30% trailing
stop loss.
So, at what price do you then sell the
stock?
Well, 30% of $200 is $60, yeah, I had to
work my math a while in my head. So,
this means if the price declined $60
from the high, this is where you exit
this trade. So, in this case, let's say
for example, the
stock declined to about $140.
You would then sell the stock and made a
gain of about 40% from your entry point.
So, you can see that as the stock price
progressively move in your favor, let's
say it now goes up to
from 200 it goes up to $300. Your
trailing stop loss will now be at $210,
all right, because 30% of $300 is $90,
300 minus 90 is $210. So, as the
price as the market moves in your favor,
your trailing stop loss also goes up,
right? To help help you lock in those
gains, right? And to allow you to ride
the trend, but at the same time giving
it some breathing room so you don't get
stopped out of your trade prematurely.
Next,
follow the price, which means simply,
you know, buy high and sell higher or,
you know, short low
and cover back lower, right? So, as a
trend follower, you're not trying to buy
the lows or sell at the absolute highs.
You're just simply trying to capture the
meat of the move. So, let me explain to
you what meat of the move is. So, let's
say you're looking to buy often, right?
Buying breakouts.
The trend continues and when it starts
to reverse, over here you sell. So, the
meat of the move is this part over here.
Okay? This is what I call mom. Mommy.
Meat of the move. As a trend follower,
that's all you're trying to aim for, the
meat of the move. And this is achieved,
right? By buying highs, buying breakout,
and then using a trailing stop loss to
ride the trend till it ends.
Now, after reading this book, I faced an
issue. The book explained what trend
following is about, but it doesn't
show you how to apply
to the real world of trading. Like for
my own trading account, you know, I
faced questions like, when exactly do I
buy? When do I sell? How do I manage my
risk? Which markets should I be trading
and why? So, it's like someone telling
you, "Rayner, just go and cook a
delicious meal." But it doesn't give me
the recipe on how to do it.
Now, don't get me wrong. Trend Following
is a great book, but for me it wasn't
enough. I also needed a book that gave
me the actual trend following recipe.
And this brings me to my next book. The
third book is Following the Trend by
Andreas Clenow.
This is a game changer for me.
Because it's the first book I've read
that actually gave me a complete trading
system. This means
it tells you when exactly to buy, when
to sell, how much to buy and sell,
everything
revealed to you in a step-by-step
manner.
It even gives me the back test results
of the trading system, so you can
actually verify the performance on your
part. That's huge, right? Because most
trading books, they don't tell you the
results of their strategy or systems.
They give you the theory, but you've no
idea whether it actually works or not.
So, this one gives you a complete
trading system backed by data. And
because of this book, I managed to take
what I've learned and differ my own
trend following system that I use even
to this day.
As you can see, this is the result of
the trend following system that I've
developed and
it has generated about 3,500% since
2000. And what's really interesting
about trend following is that it tends
to thrive during a crisis or recession
period. For example, in 2000 is a
dot-com bubble, up about 25%. 2008 is
the Lehman Brother collapse, the
financial crisis.
2020, you have COVID. 2022, you have the
Russia-Ukraine war. So, you can see that
during such difficult times in the
market, trend following tends, right, to
make a killing, to make a profit.
At the same time, trend following is not
without its flaws, right? When the
markets are choppy, when it's in a
range, it bleeds money and you go into a
drawdown. And another thing about trend
following is, as mentioned earlier, it
has a low winning rate, about 40%
usually. This means you can take years
sometimes to even get out of a drawdown.
And it's painful to sit through one,
especially if this is the only
strategy you're trading and the stock
market is making a new equity high.
So, I wondered to myself, you know,
besides trend following, you know, what
other proven trading strategies are
there out there?
Now, I wasn't looking for, you know,
feel-good trading strategies that look
good on paper, but rather I wanted books
that provide a complete trading system
with back test results so I can verify
these results for myself.
And eventually, I chanced upon this
book. Now, the fourth book is short-term
trading strategies that work by Larry
Connors and Cesar Alvarez. So, shout out
to Cesar if you're watching this, right?
So, Cesar is someone I'm very grateful
for because he helps me develop many of
my trading systems. So, hello. Thank
you, Cesar, if you're watching this.
So, this book The idea behind this book
is it focus entirely on mean reversion
trading. So, unlike trend following that
looks to write trends in the market,
mean reversion trading looks to capture
just one swing, one move in the market.
So, let me give you an example. So, a
mean reversion trading system typically
look for stocks that are in an uptrend,
waits for it to make a pullback, usually
stocks with that are oversold, they're
looking then to buy.
And when the stock does make a rally,
boing, right? We then would sell.
And as you can see, right, a mean
reversion trading system just looks to
capture this one small piece of the
move.
Unlike trend following which looks to
write the entire trend, to write the
wave, to endure the the pullbacks along
the way, for mean reversion trading is
not just
a small bounce, one swing up higher, one
move up higher, that's it. We're going
to sell for a profit.
So, what I like about this book is it
focus entirely on mean reversion
trading, this concept, this strategy,
and it gives you a number of
mean reversion trading systems as ideas
to actually develop your own, right? So,
the strategy is simple, mean reversion
trading, but this one strategy can be
used to develop into multiple trading
systems, just like you know how a father
can have, you know, five sons, five
daughters, etc. Right? So, same thing,
right? A mean reversion strategy, right,
can have multiple systems, right, to
spin off from it. So, this gives This
book gives you different ideas you can
consider. It gives you the exact trading
rules, when to buy, when to sell, and
the backtest data to support, right? So,
you can actually verify it whether it
works or not. Now, there are a few
lessons that I've actually learned from
this book. So, number one, you don't
need a stop loss for a mean reversion
trading system. So, this is actually
something I learned from Cesar. So, I
believe he shared a blog post sometime
ago where if you have a stop loss, a
price-based stop loss for such a trading
system, it tends to make
the results worse. So, what Caesar did
is that, you know, he tried with a 10%
stop loss, 20, 30, 40, 50. And what he
found is that the wider the stop loss,
the better the results of these trading
systems. And to the point where having
no price-based stop loss is usually the
best for the mean reversion trading
system. But again, don't take my word
for it. Go and do the testing and then
find it out for yourself.
So, now without a price-based stop loss,
so how do you then manage your risk? So,
a mean reversion trading system
typically manages
the risk using two techniques: position
sizing and a time-based stop loss. So,
let me explain. So, how does position
sizing help? So, let's say you have a
$100,000 trading account. Okay? For a
mean reversion trading system, you're
not going to, you know, put all your
money into
one stock. All right? Because that's a
lot of risk, right? If the stock goes to
zero, your account goes to zero. So,
what it does is that it would split your
capital into, let's say, 10 different
stocks.
And each stock, you all right, you
typically get about
you get 10% of your capital. So, if you
think about this, all right, if you buy
10 stocks, one stock goes to zero, you
lose everything in that one stock.
There's still that nine other stocks
down there. So, if one stock goes to
zero, you will lose
10% of your account, which is painful,
but it wouldn't blow up your account.
So, you can see that even despite one
stock going to zero, which is quite
slim, your your account will probably be
in the 10% drawdown. Compared to all
your money in that one stock, if it goes
to zero, you would wipe out your
account. So, that is how proper position
sizing, how spreading your bets across
different stocks will help you manage
your risk.
And another thing is that it also uses a
time-based stop loss. So, what do I mean
by this is a mean reversion trading
system typically buys on the pullback.
Okay? And usually within a few days, we
are expecting the market to make a
bounce. Toying higher. So, if after a
few days the stock doesn't really move
or make a bounce, we would then exit the
trade even though
you know, it it it it it isn't it isn't
uh what do you call it? Even though it
isn't moving anywhere and we're not
going to going to give it any more time,
right? Because based on
on testing, right? Usually if stocks
after a few days doesn't make a bounce,
it's better to use your money, your
capital and put it into another
potential mean reversion trading setup
where the other stock has a higher
probability of making a bounce. So,
that's why we use a time-based stop loss
to get out of stocks that are not going
anywhere and at the same time also to
help us manage our risk, you know, just
in case it doesn't go anywhere and then
suddenly collapse, right? So, by the
time before it can collapse, right? We
already out of that stock as well.
Now, the best part is this is that mean
reversion trading complements trend
following. They are like, you know,
Batman and Robin, peanut butter and
jelly, Tom and Jerry, right? So, hit the
subscribe button, right? If you're
someone who loves the cartoon Tom and
Jerry as well.
So, when trend following, right? It
doesn't usually do well when markets are
choppy or range bound, right? And this
is where a mean reversion trading system
usually tends to do well. At the same
time when mean reversion trading system
struggles in a bear market, that's when
trend following tends to do well. So,
when you combine them, right? Your
results, you know, go through the roof,
right? So, let's have a look at this.
So, this over here, as you can see, this
is a STF stands for systematic trend
following system and MRT stands for mean
reversion trading system. On its own,
right? Both of these systems have losing
years like, you know, STF lost in 2009,
2012, 2023, etc. But when you combine
them, right? This is where you you get
you get the results on this third
column. You're able to profit almost
every single year whether it's a bull
market, a bear market or even during a
recession. You can see that in 2000 dot
com bubble, yeah, you're up almost close
to 92%. 2008 financial crisis, up 48%.
COVID, up close to 20%. Russia-Ukraine
war, up close to 20%. And
the losing year that you had was in 2023
for a minuscule 5%. And that's the power
of, you know,
having trend following and mean
reversion trading system working hand in
hand. Can you see how powerful this is?
So, at this point, right, I was then
wondering, you know, you know, who else
adopt such an approach to trading? I
wanted to find out which other traders
out there, you know, have multiple
trading systems working for them. And
this is where I chance upon this next
book. The fifth book is
Automated Stock Trading Systems by Loren
Brent Stovall. And it's the book that
helped me
piece the puzzles together, right? This
book teaches you
multiple trading systems, different
types of strategy, you know, like mean
reversion, trend following, systems that
go long, systems that go short, even,
right? And just like the earlier books,
right, it gives you the exact trading
rules along with the back test results,
so you can verify the data for yourself.
And by now, you would have realized that
I love such trading books that gives you
the rules and back tested results.
And with this knowledge, you can, you
know, go out there and develop trading
systems to profit in different market
conditions, right? Like what Loren has
done. And if I'm not wrong today, he has
like 55 trading systems working for him.
I can't even handle three of my monkeys
at home, and he has, you know, 55
trading systems working for him, right?
So, the lesson is this, right, is that,
you know, you can diversify
a strategy across different time frames,
across different markets. So, for
example, trend following strategy,
right, you can diversify, you know, by
having a long-term trend following
system, a medium-term trend following
system, and even a short-term trend
following system. They're all trend
following, but the type of trends that
you capture can be different, right,
whether is it long, short, or medium
type of trends.
Now, today, I myself, I trade about 10
trading systems, and it wouldn't be
possible without these traders and the
books that they have written, right? So,
credit goes all out to them, right, for
being so generous with their work so
that, you know, someone like me can
profit off their sharings and learnings.
Now, at the same time, right? You can
learn all these different strategies and
systems out there, but if you want to
get rich,
it is not enough, right? And this last
book explains why. The last book is The
Psychology of Money by Morgan Housel.
It doesn't teach you a single trading
strategy, not one indicator or a chart
pattern.
But, it's possibly the most important
book.
Let me share with you a story that I
learned from the book. Ronald Read was a
janitor from rural Vermont. He fixed car
at a gas station for 25 years, and you
know, swept floors at a
departmental store for 17 years.
He bought a two-bedroom house at the age
of 38 and lived there
for the rest of his life. Simple
stuff, you know.
When he died in 2014 at the age of 92,
his net worth was over $8 million. A
janitor,
$8 million. No secret strategy,
no insider information, no inheritance.
He simply saved throughout his life,
lived frugally, and you know, stayed
invested in the markets. At the same
time, there is this guy called Richard
Fusconi. He's a Harvard graduate, a Wall
Street executive, and owns an 18,000
square foot home that costs $500,000 a
month to maintain. Half a million
dollars a month to maintain. And during
2008,
Richard was hit financially and
eventually declared a bankrupt. So,
what's
the lesson in sharing with you, you
know, the lives of these two people? So,
I think this is where Morgan Housel
quote kind of sum it up really well.
It's this, financial success is not a
hard skill. It's a soft skill, where how
you behave is more important than what
you know. So, if you ask me, the secret
to getting rich from trading lies in
this formula. You must have an edge in
the markets, sound risk management so
you don't blow up, and to be disciplined
in following your rules and compounding
your returns over time.
And when you can do that, the amount of
money you can make is staggering. Okay,
so let me show you this man over here.
He is none other than Warren Buffett.
And do you know that
among the billions, the hundreds of
billions of dollars that he has today,
most of his money, or 97% of his money,
came after his 65th birthday. So, you
can see over here, this portion over
here, from his 60s to his 90s, this is
where he make the most of his money.
Why is that? That's because he allowed
the power of compound entrance, compound
interest to work for decades, and to let
the magic play out. So, that's how it is
important, right? To not only have
discipline to follow your rules, but
allow it to compound over time.
So, as you can as you can see over here,
it is important to have an edge, right?
Because without an edge, right? Then if
you're just going to compound with
discipline on something that doesn't
work, then you're just going to lose
money in the long run. So, it's
important to have an edge with sound
risk management. And as you know, I've
shared with you a numerous books that,
you know, can give you insights to
develop your own trading systems. But if
you want a shortcut, you want something
kind of like handed to you on a silver
platter, you know, trading strategies,
systems that are already backed by data,
you can actually get my free training
over here. Okay, called trading
strategies that work. And in this
training, I'll teach you three specific
trading systems, a mean reversion system
that has generated 2800% over the last
25 years, a futures trend following
system, and a momentum trading system.
And all of these system, they are backed
by data. I've given give you the
backtest research, the report. I'll walk
you through the trading rules, the chart
examples so you can see how this trading
system works. And hopefully, right, to
give you an edge in the market so you
can now go out there and make the money
that you deserve.
And along the way, I'll give you the
training slides of the the PDF slides of
this training, the trading strategies
cheat sheet, and the backtest report of
the different trading systems that I'll
be teaching you. So, if you're
interested to grab
this free training, you can go down to
the link tradingwithrayner.com/go
or just scan this QR code and I'll send
this free training to your email, right?
So, I'll also put the link somewhere
below this video so it's easier for you
to access. So, with that's it. I wish
you good luck, good trading.
I will talk to you soon.